

Sreejith Vidyadharan

Professional summary

Highly driven Data Scientist, with 3 years of experience in machine learning, data mining and cloud computing. Creative problem solver, focused on continuous improvement and optimisation with 11+ years experience in telecommunication sector. Passionate learner of anything new, with advanced programming and cloud computing proficiency.

Work history

Omdena - Machine Learning Engineer

Liverpool

12/2022 - Current

Omdena Serbia Chapter

• Developed a time-series AI predictive system to mitigate flood risks in Belgrade using historical weather and hydrological data.

Omdena Lublin Chapter

• Developed a conversational AI chatbot for people affected by high inflation and increased cost of living providing financial assistance.

B.S.N.L - Data Scientist

Thiruvalla, Kerala, India 07/2018 - 09/2021

- Implemented natural language processing techniques to analyse customer feedback and identified key drivers of satisfaction, leading to a 10% increase in customer satisfaction scores.
- Collecting bandwidth usage data from transmission CPAN nodes, and from other MPLS and mobile divisions and creating a timeseries prediction for forecasting future requirements for augmenting current transmission systems with additional line cards.
- Developed machine learning models to predict customer churn and collaborated with marketing team to design targeted retention campaigns, resulting in a 15% decrease in churn rate.
- Predicting allocation of new nodes and additional bandwidth resources connecting each nodes between transmission stations based on past data.
- Develop data-driven presentations out of telecom data, and create comparison charts and reports based on past vs present trends.

✓ sreejith_v@outlook.com

+447825127188

• 18 Redgrave Street, Liverpool, Merseyside L7 0ED

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/sreejith vidyadharan

Websites, portfolios

• https://sreejithvn.github.io/

Certifications

AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate - 98% AWS Certified Developer Associate - 95% Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA)

Associate - 86% Microsoft Certified Azure Developer Associate - 86%

Microsoft Certified Azure Data Scientist

Skills

- Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Keras, Streamlit, Telnetlib), SQL, PySpark, Boto3
- AWS services: MLOps, SageMaker, Glue, Athena, EC2, ECS, S3, DynamoDB, RDS, Data Wrangler
- Natural Language Processing: SpaCy, Textacy, NLTK, Hugging-face Transformers, Gensim, TextBlob, Word

B.S.N.L - Telecom Network Operation Engineer

Thiruvalla, Kerala, India 03/2010 - 06/2018

- Created an OS agnostic desktop GUI application in python for monitoring packet transport systems, which was adopted by Network Monitoring Centre, enabling efficient parallel monitoring of multiple systems.
- Coordinating with Network Operations Centre for planning and designing new projects such as extending OTN, CPAN and 4G rollout media in BSNL.
- Implemented MPLS-TP based packet transport network in BSNL, where we carried out acceptance testing for initial rollout in our state and executed the same within 6 weeks.
- Provisioning and maintaining services via long-distance optical transmission systems such as SDH, DWDM, CPAN and OTN based on multiple vendors like Cisco, Huawei, ZTE, Tejas, UTL and FiberHome.
- Automated several manual repetitive tasks such as backing up transmission system configuration files and logging system bandwidth loads with python and bash scripts and regular cron jobs.
- Greatly appreciated by higher ups for the quick migration to packet transport systems from SDH, and for the eagerness in learning all new OAM features, by extensive research and later conducting training sessions for entire STR wing.
- Actively participated in vendor training programmes for CPAN,
 NG-SDH and OTN, and conducted industrial training sessions for college students, and was awarded a certificate of excellence for the same.

Projects

Zero-shot classification for Long text data with NLI

Tools: Transformers, PyTorch, Pandas, Streamlit, AWS EC2, Docker

Customer review analysis of Telecom data

Tools: SpaCy, Textacy, NLTK, Word Cloud, Scikit-Learn, Regex, sqlite3, Pandas

Time series energy prediction with AWS forecast

Tools: AWS Forecast, ARIMA, Prophet, Python, Pandas, Boto3, AWS S3

GUI application for monitoring CPAN transmission systems

Tools: Python, PyQt, Telnetlib

Conversational AI Chatbot for Financial Assistance

Tools: SpaCy, NLTK, Transformers, Streamlit

- Cloud, Text Classification, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modelling, Clustering
- Methods: XGBoost, Random Forests, Decision Trees, Clustering,
 Optimisation, Statistical analysis, A/B testing, Time Series, Deep Learning,
 Reinforcement Learning
- Development: Git, GitHub, Linux/Unix, Mac, Windows
- Deployment: AWS, Azure, Docker
- Networking: L2/L3 Routing and switching, Network security and Administration, L2 VPN, MPLS-TP, SDH, CPAN, DWDM, OTN, FTTH, Wireshark, GNS3, Ethernet and SDH Analyser, OTDR
- Machine Learning, Cloud Computing,
 Data Analysis, Data Visualisation,
 Product Development, Analytical
 Skills, Problem Solving, Planning, Data
 Modelling, Statistics, Research,
 Communication Skills, Written
 Communication

Education

12/2022

University of Liverpool

Liverpool

Master of Science: Data Science and Artificial Intelligence - 80%

07/2009

Government Engineering College

Thrissur

Bachelor of Technology: Electronics and Communication - 74%